本字幕由3c区提供，最新电影下载，请上3c区(www.3cqu.com)
3c区(www.3cqu.com)- 第一时间发布最新最好看的电影
前情提要
我收集到的情报显示
The information I've received suggests to me that the
德国人正在准备一场不同的战斗
Germans are preparing for a different kind of combat.
又一个你关于
Is this another one of
可能的战争的悲观预言么?
your gloomy predictions about the likelihood of war?
我该嫉妒这个中校么
Should I be jealous of the Colonel?
我爱上你了 Anna
I'm in love with you, Anna.
我都忘了这种感觉了
I'd forgotten these feelings.
他们抓走了Max
They took Max!
他们就像拘捕一个普通犯人一样在夜里抓走了他
They just took him in the night like a common criminal.
我需要跟她谈谈  我需要一个解释的机会
I need to talk to her. I need a chance to explain.
朋友 她现在满腹愧疚 怒火中烧
My friend, she's filled with guilt and anger,
因为如果她没有陷入爱情 发生在Max身上的事
because what happened to Max would not have happened
原本就不会发生
if she had not fallen in love.
如果要我说服巴黎挽救你们的老命
If I'm going to convince Paris to save your skins,
我需要名字
I need a name.
Chaika  就是这个
Chaika! That was it!
有个人可能会对你有帮助
There is a man who might help you.
他曾经是一位古代语言学教授
He was once a professor of ancient languages.
但现在他正躲在
Now he is hiding in
捷克斯洛伐克 因为盖世太保在追捕他
Czechoslovakia because he's hunted by the Gestapo.
你应该即刻动身
You should go there quickly.
因为恐怕 他已经命不久矣了
I fear he may not be long for this world.
===BTM字幕组出品===
本字幕仅供交流 切勿商用
翻译：蝴蝶 小羽 小十 果果
校对：宸宸
后期：缨
压制：迷毁 master
华沙间谍
我要去医院
异想天开
我的耳朵都快掉下来了
上校  有您的电话
Colonel! A phone call.
能不能等到我早茶之后再去接呢
Won't it keep till after my morning coffee?
发生了一场枪击案
There's been a shooting.
你是Jean-Francois Mercier中校
You are Colonel Jean-Francois Mercier,
陆军武官
Military Attache
任职于华沙的法国大使馆
at the French Embassy in Warsaw.
但那并不全是你工作的全部 是不是 中校
But that's not all you do, is it, Colonel?
你又是干什么的呢
What is it you do?
我追踪像你这样的人
I go after people like you,
像你这样 破坏我祖国安全的人
who undermine the security of my country.
你帮助一对俄国特工夫妇叛逃了
You helped a Russian couple to defect.
为什么这么做
Why?
他们担心自己的生命受到威胁
They were afraid for their lives.
所以 作为交换他们提供给你你想要的情报信息
Presumably offered information in exchange for your help?
干咱们这行的游戏规则 恩?
That's the way things are in our business, hm?
我想知道他们透露给你的情报是什么
I'd like to know what that information was.
我不会告诉你的 你这是在浪费时间
I'm not going to tell you so this is a waste of time.
唔
Hm.
中校
Colonel,
我们两国并没有交战
our countries are not at war.
恩 是暂时没有
Not yet, no.
希望永远别起战端
Let's hope never.
我们都是见不得光的人
We're both men who work in the shadows.
我想 你跟这儿的一位年轻姑娘
You're involved with a young woman
有千丝万缕的关联 是吗
here, I believe?
Anna Skarbek
Anna Skarbek?
那跟这事儿有什么关系
How is that relevant?
我的重点在于 咱俩都得有命活着回去
My point is that we have lives to go back to.
我呢 有家有室 还有一个尚未出世的孩子
Myself, I am married with a new child on the way.
你要怎么才能再见你的家人呢
How will you ever see your family again?
你永远都逃不出波兰了
You'll never get out of Poland.
你的手下一个已经死了
You have one man dead,
另一个就像被宰的猪一样流血
another bleeding like a pig...
而且你的汽车还在漏油
And your car is leaking gasoline.
请让我们独处好么 护士
Could you leave us, nurse?
你看见她跟我笑了吗  她迷上我了
Did you see that smile? She wants me.
你感觉怎么样
How are you feeling?
言之尚早  怎么回事儿
Too early to tell. What happened?
汽车爆炸的时候我们到了
We arrived when the car blew up.
那德国人呢
And the Germans?
一个在停尸房 另外两个被我们关起来了
One in the morgue, two in our cells.
德国大使馆跟我们要人
Their embassy wants them back.
我们跟他们说不可能
We've told them not a chance.
你的大使馆说是要来探望你
Your embassy will be paying you a visit.
唔
Mm.
我想在他们来之前离开这儿
I want to be out of here before that.
我才不想给他们一个阻止我的借口
I don't want to give them an excuse to stop me.
阻止你干什么
Doing what?
你知道我不能告诉你
You know I can't tell you.
但我需要出趟远门儿
But I need to take a trip.
帮我离开这儿吧
Help me out of here.
就这么离开?
Looking like that?
给我你的大衣
Lend me your coat.
这儿  就是这里
Here. In here.
对不起 先生们 他看上去已经离开了
I'm sorry, sir, he seems to have gone.
1938年3月
捷克斯洛伐克 Tsesin
您在等人吗
Waiting for someone?
看来她放我鸽子了
Looks like she stood me up.
Halbach先生
Herr Halbach.
Herr Halbach!
什么事
你想要什么
我非常重要的消息带给您
我们能单独谈谈吗
Can we talk in private?
你不是德国人
You're not German.
不是  能进去聊聊吗
No. Can we go inside?
把手放在我能看见的地方!
Keep your hands where I can see them!
请不要把这东西挥来挥去的
Please don't wave that around.
你看上去不是那种惯用枪支火器的人
You don't look like the kind of man who's used to firearms.
当然不是 我是个老师
I'm not, I'm a teacher.
但这并不意味着我不会使用它
It doesn't mean I won't use it.
你想从我这儿得到什么
What do you want with me?
是你的政治主张把我带到你面前的
It's your politics that bring me here.
你不会留我活口的
You won't take me alive.
敢动一动我就立刻杀了你
I'll kill you if you try.
我不是你的敌人
I'm not your enemy.
那你他妈的是谁
Then who the hell are you?
一个朋友
I'm a friend.
而且我必须指出
And I should point out
想找到你实在是轻而易举
it wasn't all that difficult to find you.
跪下  现在
On your knees. Now!
Halbach先生
您晚上用晚餐吗
今晚不会
谢谢你Franz
我是来给你提供避难所的 Halbach先生
I'm here to offer you sanctuary, Herr Halbach.
你能在这里待多久  几个月  几年
How long can you stay here? Months? Years?
大概吧
Perhaps.
希特勒已经攻占了奥地利
Hitler has already marched into Austria.
这儿就是他下一个目标
He'll be here next.
接下来你又会去哪儿
Then where will you go?
你说的避难所到底是什么
What exactly is this sanctuary?
一本瑞士护照和五万瑞士法郎
A Swiss passport and 50,000 Swiss Francs.
那可是一大笔钱啊
That is a great deal of money.
请理解 我们不会要求您
Understand, we are not
去做任何针对德国人民和你祖国的事
asking you to do anything against the German
只要针对希特勒的政权
people or your homeland. Only against the Hitler regime.
那作为回报我得做点什么呢  暗杀什么人?
And what would I have to do for all this? Kill somebody?
只是去拜访一位故友 带着一份请求去
Visit an old friend, with a request
开给他和你所得到的一样的条件
and the same offer we're making to you.
然后你们俩就都能重获新生了
Then both of you can lead new lives.
富有 安全的人生
Wealthy, safe lives.
这是预付款
Consider this an advance.
你怎么确定我就不会卷款而逃呢
How do you know I won't take this and disappear?
因为如果那样你就是偷了这笔钱 从我们这里
Because then you will have stolen it... From us.
那谁又是那位"故友"呢
And who is this "Old friend"?
你过去在黑锋的同伴 现在在IN6工作
A comrade of yours from the Black Front who works in IN6.
他在俄国的化名是Chaika
His Russian alias is Chaika.
现在我知道你在查什么了
Now I see what you're after.
可他现在在德国
But he is in Germany.
我不能去那儿  我在德国是通缉犯
I can't go there. I'm a wanted criminal in Germany.
你会拿到一份瑞士护照 跟我的一样
You'll have a Swiss passport, as have I.
我们是来自同一家公司的推销员
We're salesmen for the same company.
我们会待在一个小宾馆里
We'll stay in a small hotel
你只有一个晚上需要露面
and you'll be visible for only one evening.
什么时候开始这个行动
When would this be?
明天就走
We leave tomorrow.
明天  我还有课呢
Tomorrow? But I have classes.
就说你这位教授先生身体抱恙
The Herr Professor is indisposed.
明天十点之前给我出现在车站
Be at the station before ten.
我在Tsesin有位朋友
I have a friend here in Tsesin
一位对我来说非常重要的朋友
who has made a great difference to me.
我想我应该跟她好好道个别
I should like to say goodbye.
我很抱歉 那是不可能的事
I'm sorry, that won't be possible.
还是给她寄个明信片吧
Send her a postcard.
你们的大使馆已经把跟你们的关系洗脱的干干净净了
Your embassy has washed their hands of you.
他们说你们是
They say you were acting
自发行动 未经任何当局许可
on your own initiative, without any authority.
所以你们不会被遣返德国  而是留在这里
So you are not going back to Germany. You will stay here.
这里是为永远不会回家的人们准备的监狱
This is a prison for people who never go home.
这是你的 Braun先生
This is yours, Herr Braun.
而我是Lombardo先生
And I am Herr Lombardo.
我们必须给你准备点儿更合适的衣服
We must get you some more suitable clothes.
你的家人可以用你的新护照旅行了
Your family can travel on your new passport.
不 不 不 已经尘埃落定了
No, no, no, that's all finished,
我过去的人生
that part of my life.
我转入地下工作的时候就把他们送走了
When I went underground, I sent them away,
为了他们的安全
for their safety.
很快我就不知道他们的行踪了
I no longer know where they are
他们也不再知道我身在何处
and nor do they know where I am.
你的朋友Chaika有家庭吗
Does your friend Chaika have a family?
有的
Yes.
他的真名是什么呢
And his real name?
Johannes Elter
Johannes Elter.
- 你们过去关系好吗   - 哦 当然好
- Were you close?  - Oh, yes.
我们最初都那么热爱我们的政党
We both loved the party
一个战败国家的崛起
at the start the rising up
民族自尊心的重塑 以及贫穷潦倒的终结
of a defeated nation, the return of pride, the end of poverty.
后来我们才知道究竟发生了什么
And then we saw what was happening.
我的祖母还是犹太人
And I have a Jewish grandmother.
他在参谋总部是做什么工作的
What does he do in the General Staff?
他是书记  但是处于局势的中心
He's a clerk. But he's in the thick of things.
他赌博吗
Does he gamble?
不赌  他是个一毛不拔的铁公鸡
No. He pinches every pfennig.
寻花问柳吗?
Visit whores?
花他自己的钱么?
And spend his own money?
那他应该会对我的条件非常感兴趣
So he should be interested in my offer.
好了 Lombardo先生
Well, Herr Lombardo...
那取决于他有多贪生怕死了
That depends on how afraid he is.
华沙
你怎么知道我在华沙
How did you know I was in Warsaw?
知道这些是我的职责所在
It's my business to know.
你要在这儿待很久吗
Will you be here long?
不会的  我是过来关了公寓
No. I came to close the apartment.
这儿到处都是书  您请自便吧
There are books everywhere. Help yourself.
很遗憾Mercier不在城里
Pity Mercier is not in town.
他会很想见你的
He would want to see you.
我没心思见他 Antoni
I have no wish to see him, Antoni.
Anna 我对国内安全的所有事了如指掌
Anna, I know everything that goes on in Internal Security.
并不是Mercier要求驱逐Max的
The request to expel Max did not come from Mercier.
消息是从法国来的
It came from the French.
不是从Mercier那
Not from Mercier.
那从谁那里来
Then from whom?
这我还不是十分确定
I'm not exactly sure.
我还以为你无所不知呢  显然是我高估了
I thought you knew everything. Apparently you don't.
我知道的是他很爱你
I know he loves you.
如果不是这样的话
If he didn't,
我早就想勾搭你了
I would try to seduce you.
你这是要去哪儿呢
Where do you go from here?
国联要派我去西班牙
The League is sending me to Spain.
西班牙  陷入内战漩涡的国家啊
Spain? The country's in the middle of civil war.
我要去就外籍人士的释放
I'll be negotiating the
进行谈判  我明天就走
release of foreign nationals. I leave tomorrow.
Jean-Francois在哪儿
Where is Jean-Francois?
我想 他正在前往巴黎的路上
On his way to Paris, I believe.
巴黎
Paris?
请出示护照
Paesse, bitte.
你们两个都是瑞士人  你们两个一起旅行
You're both Swiss? You're travelling together?
我们为同一家公司工作
We work for the same company.
柏林
你们的人就不能准备个像样一点的旅店吗
Couldn't your people afford a decent hotel?
太显眼了
Too conspicuous.
看这两位迷人的绅士 Trudl
要在这儿过夜吗 男孩们
可能要呆三个晚上
五个马克一晚上 先交定金
也许
他们想住一起呢
谢谢
Danke.
那么 你要去见Elter了
So, you're meeting with Elter.
如果他不愿意 你就提醒他
If he's reluctant, remind him -
是希特勒和他的党派
it's Hitler and his clique
想要把整个国家都卷入战争
that want to take the country into war.
如果战争来临 受苦受难的都是德国人民
And if it comes, it's the German people who will suffer.
啊哦 喻以大义
Ah, the moral argument.
那会把警察引来的
That will bring the police!
他们是党卫队  警察不会过来找他们麻烦的
They're SS. The police won't bother them.
你为什么要跟他们交待我的事
Why did you tell them about me?
我对你可是一如既往的忠诚
I have always been a faithful friend to you.
正因为此我才会来的
That's why I'm here.
你能在盖世太保的监牢外面苟延残喘多久
How long can you stay out of a Gestapo cellar?
何况你一直是希特勒的眼中钉肉中刺
And you'll only be harming Hitler.
我想我们得撤了
I think we have to leave.
大厅里头有个男人 是个党卫队的中队长
There was a man in the lobby, an SS Oberscharfuehrer.
我想他认出我了
I think he recognised me.
何以见得
From where?
我被盖世太保缠住询问了好几个小时的问题
I've spent many hours being questioned by the Gestapo.
他本该在那的
He could have been there.
快整理行装
Pack your things.
- 你不能这么做   - 上车
- You can't do this!  - Get in.
这太疯狂了
This is madness!
你不能偷走这台车
You can't steal this car.
他们会在这儿消磨好几个小时呢
They'll be in there for hours.
那么 Elter的事 怎么样了
So, Elter. What happened?
他还在犹豫
He's unsure.
第一班渡轮会在八点钟起锚
The first ferry's at eight.
你在对岸就能搭上去哥本哈根的火车了
You can get a train to Copenhagen at the other side.
一到那里 你就能随心所欲的过日子了
Once you're there, you can do whatever you like.
我都快忘了那种不用东躲西藏的日子了
I'd almost forgotten that kind of life.
给你的钱都存放在苏黎世银行  我们决不食言
The funds are in Zurich. We're true to our word.
你做的这一切有意义吗
Will all this make any difference?
我必须相信这有意义
I have to believe it will.
Halbach告诉我你总是第一个到
Halbach told me you always arrived first.
这样在其他人来齐之前
So we have a few moments
我们就有几分钟的闲暇来谈谈话
before the others get here.
我不能那么做
I can't do it!
你叫我做的事情 那实在实在危险了
What you're asking, it is too dangerous.
如果有更多的钱给你
If there was more money,
你是不是就会觉得它没那么危险了
would you find it less dangerous?
你不理解
You must understand...
我很理解贪欲   - 你必须明白
I understand greed.  - You must understand...
贪欲让我们的交易简单很多了
It makes things very simple between us.
你这是叫我出卖我的国家
You are asking me to betray my country.
你原来就出卖过 对苏联人
You've betrayed it before, to the Soviets.
Chaika  这难道不是你的代号吗
Chaika. Wasn't that your code name?
盖世太保对这一切肯定有兴趣
The Gestapo would be interested to know that.
咱们按约定见面
We'll meet as arranged.
这并不是贪欲作祟
This is not about greed.
总有一天 我会离开的
One day, I will have to leave.
你的金钱就是为那一刻而准备
Your money is for that.
为了给我的家人以安定和幸福 如果情况允许的话
For my family's safety, God willing.
我想你一定有子女吧
You have children, I believe.
有三个
Three.
我不能告诉他们我对希特勒的看法
I cannot tell them of my feelings for Hitler,
对眼下所发生的事的看法
for what is happening here
因为他们的老师 他们相信眼下的一切
because their teachers, they believe it all.
我的长子
My eldest,
他和那边的孩子穿着一模一样的制服
he wears the same uniform as the ones over there.
那么 这件事要怎么运作
So, how will this work?
同一时间 同一地点
Same place, same time,
每隔一周 会有人来这里取走东西
every other week, someone will pick up the drop.
在内心深处
In my heart,
我一直就是个叛徒
I have always been a traitor.
他给我的大部分东西都毫无意义
Much of what he gave me was pointless.
但是但是呈给你看的这些不是
But everything you see here is not.
这是一份阿登高地的森林调查图
It's a forest survey map of the Ardennes,
法国北部，比利时东南部及卢森堡北部，默兹河的东西两方的高原。
它是第一次及第二次世界大战中重要战役的场所， 1944年十二月和1945年一月在巴尔基战役中引人瞩目
一份关于德国坦克射程的报告
a report on the range of German tanks,
还有一份是关于地面清障的
another on ground clearances.
我感兴趣的恰好是没提到的那些
What interests me is what's not here.
关于马其诺防线什么也说
Nothing on the Maginot Line.
法国在第一次世界大战后，为防德军入侵而在其东北边境地区构筑的筑垒配系。
以法国陆军部长A．-L．-R．马奇诺的姓氏命名
也没提我们的东境防御系统
Nothing on our defence system on the Eastern Frontier.
要塞 地堡 碉堡都没提到
No forts, no bunkers, no pillboxes.
确实如此 这也证实了我们最担心的事
Exactly. It confirms what we feared most.
他们开着坦克穿过比利时森林而来
They're coming with tanks through the Belgian forests.
我想这些应该能说服那些不相信的人
Well, this should persuade the unbelievers.
这下我们能应对他们了
Now we'll be ready for them.
Jean-Francois 干得漂亮
You've done well, Jean-Francois.
我已经举荐你
I've recommended that you
去总参谋部工作了
take up a position here in General Staff.
我待在华沙已经没有任何意义了
There's nothing to keep me in Warsaw anymore.
谢谢你 长官
Thank you, sir.
- 你好   - 可把你盼来了
- Hello.- Finally!
我老哥的热情造访
A visit from my big brother!
热烈欢迎
Welcome.
你在这儿干了多久了
How long have you worked here?
有一阵了
A while now.
Etienne也有对私人客户的古董业务
Etienne also deals in art for private clients.
我可以帮你找些精美绝伦的宝贝装点宅邸
I could find you something vibrant and cheerful for the estate.
任何东西都好过那些骑在马背上的祖先们
Anything's better than those gloomy ancestors on horseback.
你很早以前就音讯全无
I'm so out of touch with you.
我都不知道你住在哪儿
I don't even know where you live.
我们住的地方离这就隔着三条街
Oh, we only live three streets away.
你们
We?
我和Armand
Armand and I.
看来我还有些事情不知道
Something else I didn't know about you.
Armand是何许人也
What does Armand do?
他在夜总会里弹钢琴
He plays piano in a nightclub,
所以我想你恐怕不会同意我俩在一起
so you probably won't approve.
- 你不是和那个谁...   - Daniel
- Weren't you with, erm...? - Daniel.
对 我挺喜欢Daniel的 他怎么了
Yes, I rather liked Daniel. What happened to him?
他遇到了一个卖蓝铃花的姑娘
A Bluebell girl happened.
这很荒唐 那姑娘比他还高4英寸
Which is absurd,she's four inches taller than he is.
所以你在Armand身上找慰藉
So you found solace in Armand?
比那正经多了
It's more serious than that.
你上次写信给我的时候你还在恋爱中呢
There was a lady in your life the last time you wrote to me.
我早跟你说了要去追求她
I told you to pursue her.
我追了
I did.
然后呢
And?
我想我已经失去她了
I think I may have lost her.
我是Anna Skarbek
Anna Skarbek.
是我
'It's me.'
Jean-Francois 是你吗
Jean-Francois?
你怎么知道我在这儿
'How did you know I was here?'
我打电话给国际联盟  他们最终给了我你的号码
I called the League.They finally gave me a number.
- 你在哪儿   - 我在巴黎
- Where are you? - 'In Paris.'
我想接你过来住
I want you to live with me here.
我不能这么做
'I can't do that.
我知道Max的事不是你的错
'I know what happened to Max was not your fault.
我当时那么想是因为我被气昏了头
'I thought so at the time because I was angry.'
后来我发现比起自责 责备你要简单得多
Then I realised it was easier to blame you than myself.
为什么要自责
Blame yourself for what?
我连累了你 所以你们的大使就把他给驱逐出境了
I compromised you, so your Embassy had him expelled.
如果我们没有那段情事的话什么事也不会发生
'None of that would have happened if we hadn't had an affair.'
我们是相爱了!
We fell in love!
Max也是因为我们而死的
And Max is dead because we did.
我没法忘记这点
I can't forget that.
我们在一起的每一刻都会不断提醒着我
'And every moment we spend together would remind me of it.'
我必须得见见你
I have to see you.
Anna 我需要你
I need you, Anna.
没有我你照样可以活得很好
You'll survive without me,
Jean-Francois
Jean-Francois.
如果我们中的任何人活下来的话
If any of us survive at all.
鱼子酱
Caviar!
Viktor 看哪 多么奢侈啊
Look, Viktor, such luxury!
你真善良 非常感谢
How kind. Thank you so much.
你们对住的地方还满意吗
Are you comfortable where you live?
他们说称之为安全屋
They call it a safe house,
但是坦白地说 它无法给我们安全感
but to be frank, it does not feel safe.
没人保护你们吗
You have no protection?
他们盘问到情报之后就再也没有了
Not since they finished the debriefing.
既然他们已经掌握了想要知道的一切
Now that they have everything they need to know,
我们就没有利用价值了
we are dispensable.
关于Max Mostov你们跟他们说了些什么
What did you tell them about Max Mostov?
在给莫斯科的报告中未提及的都没说
Nothing that we hadn't already told Moscow in our reports,
有关他的行为和主张
about his behaviour and opinions.
你们听说他被驱逐了吗
You heard he's been deported?
是的 他们为什么要这么做
Yes. Why would they do that?
他一点都不危险
He wasn't dangerous.
你会跟他们反映
Will you remind them, Colonel
我们不应该在一个地方待的太久吗 上校
that we should never stay in one place for too long?
是的 我会的
Yes, I will.
我们现在不是上校关心的对象 Viktor
We are not the Colonel's concern now, Viktor.
是的 你们是  我保证你们的安全
Yes, you are.I guaranteed your safety.
Mercier 我代表我们所有人
'On behalf of us all, Mercier,'
我们已经迫不及待要祝贺你了
congratulations are certainly in order.
恭喜!  谢谢你们 先生们
Bravo! Thank you, gentlemen.
我很高兴地宣布
And I am delighted to announce that you are to be promoted
你已被提升为上校
to the rank of full Colonel.
我很荣幸
I'm honoured.
这是你应得的
No more than you deserve.
我们仔细梳理过那些文件
We've been through the documents with a fine-tooth comb.
- 它们无疑都指向同一个方向
- They certainly seem to point
- 我很高兴您认同我 长官
in one direction. - I'm glad you agree, sir.
当然了
Of course, we do have to
我们确实考虑过我们被误导的可能性
consider the possibility that we're being misled.
被误导
Misled?
他好到让人难以置信 不是么
Almost too good to be true, isn't he?
那个特工 叫什么名字来着
This agent - what's his name?
Johannes Elter
Johannes Elter.
对 Elter
Elter, yes.
我们中的一些人
Yes, it strikes some of us
对你这么轻易就说服他感到很怀疑
as dubious that you persuaded him so easily.
我威胁他如果他不配合 我就将他的事公布于众
I threatened him with exposure if he failed to cooperate.
即使这样
Even so,
捏造假情报也是这行最常用的伎俩 不是么
disinformation is the oldest game in the world, surely?
要做的事总是和告诉敌人们的相去甚远
Steering your enemy away from your true intention.
我不明白 你把我给你的情报搁在一边
I don't understand.
你把我给你的情报搁在一边
You're disputing the information I've given you
而与此同时你又提拔我 这说不通啊
and at the same time you're promoting me. That makes no sense.
我亲爱的Mercier 你做的工作
My dear Mercier,this work that you've done
提供了一次难能可贵的机会
has given us an invaluable insight
让我们了解到了IN6的思维方式
into the mentality of IN6.
这不是思维方式的问题 这就是事实
This is not about mentality,this is about facts!
德国人正计划从比利时入侵法国
The Germans are planning to invade France through Belgium.
这是我目睹了他们的坦克演习之后得出的结论
That was my conclusion after I witnessed their tank manoeuvres.
Elter也证实了这点
Elter confirms it!
如果你忽略了这点
If you ignore this,
你就是在将我们的国家置于危险之中
you are putting our country in peril!
我们会继续支付给Elter的报酬
We'll continue the payments to Elter
以及其他你精心策划的安排
and the other arrangements that you set up.
但是我们不会改变我们的整个军事策略的
But we do not recommend changing our entire military strategy.
祝你过得愉快 上校
Good day, Colonel.
来杯苏格兰威士忌
Scotch.
不要香槟吗
Not champagne?
我没什么值得庆祝的
I have nothing to celebrate.
你为什么选这个地方
Why did you choose this place?
因为我想让你见见Armand
Because I want you to meet Armand.
他在哪儿呢
Where is he?
看在上帝的份上 这里只有一个钢琴演奏家
Oh, for God's sake, there's only one piano player.
他年龄太大了不适合你
He's too old for you.
- 他才36   - 太老啦
- He's 36. - Too old!
你为什么情绪那么糟糕
Why are you in such a foul mood?
一言难尽 我的苏格兰威士忌呢
All sorts of reasons. Where's that Scotch?
去吧 摩西
Go down, Moses,
出自约翰逊所编歌集《美国黑人圣歌集》中的《去吧，摩西》
去那远方的埃及
Way down in Egypt's land
告诉老法老
Tell old Pharaoh
让我的人民离去
To let my people go
以色列在埃及时
When Israel was in Egypt's land
让我的人民离去
Let my people go
他们无法忍受残酷的压迫
Oppressed so hard they could not stand...
Angela女士
Lady Angela.
我想我们可以去掉那个"女士"的称呼了
I think we can dispense with "Lady".
我听说你现在待在巴黎 我想为你办场宴会
I hear you're staying in Paris. I'd like to give you a party.
我并不喜欢宴会
I'm not really a party person.
我同样觉得你不是个爱泡夜总会的人
I didn't think you were a nightclub person.
是我妹妹带我来的
My sister brought me.
这么说她不是你生命中的另一半了
Ah,so she isn't the woman in your life.
我听说是有这么一个
I've heard there is one.
疯狂的恋人 他们是这么说的
An amour fou, so they say.
不再有了
Not anymore.
天哪 她是不是太年轻了
Oh, dear. Was she too young?
我看上去像是那种专门向年轻女孩下手的男人吗
Do I look like the sort of man who preys on younger women?
这我就不清楚了
I don't know.
你从没暗示过 你喜欢我这把年纪的女人
You've given no hint that you prey on women of my age.
或许我从来都不懂女人
Perhaps I don't understand women of any age.
你有点醉了 Jean-Francois
You're a little drunk,Jean-Francois.
你觉得你能摇摇晃晃地走到波拿巴路吗
Do you think you could stagger as far as the Rue Bonaparte?
那是什么地方
What's there?
我住的地方
My apartment.
让我的人民离开
Let my people go.
醒酒生鸡蛋 从未失效过
Prairie oyster, never fails.
什么从未失效
Never fails to what?
提神醒脑的  乖乖把它喝完
Clear your head. Drink it down like a good boy.
昨晚上我情绪很糟糕 我喝多了
Last night I was in a strange mood. I drank too much.
Jean-Francois 我们在那家夜店里纵酒狂欢
Oh, Jean-Francois, we had
然后我们就上床了
fun in a boozy nightclub and then we fucked.
没有什么比那个更复杂了 你有什么计划吗
It's nothing more complicated than that. What are your plans?
我要请一段停薪假
I'm taking unpaid leave.
是时候回我的私宅里住住了
I've neglected my estate too long.
我们得保持联系
We must stay in touch.
我想我们能为国家做点什么
I think we can be of use to our countries.
我都不知道我的国家是不是认为我有用
I don't know if my country feels I'm any use at all.
那是因为Lessard以及半个总参谋部的人
Well, that's because Lessard and half your general staff
都和法兰西行动的一群法西斯分子在一起
are with that bunch of fascists in the Action Francaise.
"法兰西行动"是法国的法西斯组织
他们希望法国和德国亲密无间
They want France in bed with Germany.
能让他们远离红色恐怖的东西都行
Anything that buffers them from the red menace.
在英国有很多傻子也是这么想的
We have plenty of idiots in England who feel the same way.
我去煮咖啡
I'll make coffee.
我们应该好好照顾Rozen一家
We were supposed to look after the Rozens.
我们确实这么做的 我们给了他们钱和房子
We did. We gave them money, an apartment.
他们希望能有点安全感
They expected to live in some degree of safety,
不用害怕走在大街上
not afraid to walk down the street.
你要我批准什么 直说吧
So you'd have me sanction what, precisely?
提供一队保镖全天候保护他们
24-hour protection with a team of bodyguards
就为了一对老不中用的布尔什维克吗
for a couple of tired old Bolsheviks?
他们把知道的一切告诉了我们
They gave us everything they knew.
当他们这么做的时候
And when they did,
他们就知道以后的生活会是什么样的
they knew the life they were getting into.
光天化日之下被枪击? 那就是职业风险
A bullet in broad daylight? Occupational hazard.
我们是不是该感激俄国人差劲的枪法呢
Should be grateful the Russians can't shoot straight.
阿尔萨斯
多么讽刺啊 Viktor
How ironic, Viktor,
那个顽固的共产主义者
that die-hard communists
竟然在资本主义的光辉下安享晚年
should end up living in bourgeois splendour.
才不是呢 搞情报的可不怎么光彩
Nah, there's nothing very splendid about the plumbing.
Fernand
Fernand,
这是Viktor Rozen和他的太太Malka
this is Viktor and Malka Rozen.
- 他们要待多长时间 先生  - 不一定
- How long will they be staying, Monsieur? - Not sure.
替我盯着点村子里 田里的陌生人
Be on guard for strangers in the village, in the field.
因为我们的访客们吗
Because of our visitors?
我懂的
I understand.
谢谢你
Thank you.
我哥哥不接电话也不回信
My brother won't take phone calls or answer my letters.
你们吵架了
You have a fight?
没有
No.
他夫人死的时候他就这样子
He was like this when his wife died.
他跑到那个阴暗的地方待了好久
He went into this dark place and stayed there for a long time.
我觉得我们得去看看他
I'd like us to visit him.
哎 看见我没法让他的情绪有所改善
Well, seeing me won't improve his mood.
我不喜欢乡下 我不喜欢狗
I don't like the country. I don't like dogs.
我弹爵士钢琴而且我一天抽40根烟
I play jazz piano and I smoke 40 Gauloises a day.
求你了 就当是为了我
Please, do this for me.
你为什么不来看我
Why haven't you been to see me?
是因为华沙的夜生活很迷人吗
Is the night life of Warsaw so enticing?
我没在华沙常住 妈妈
I haven't been in Warsaw, Mother.
你就是没办法安定下来 不是吗
Hmm. You can't settle anywhere, can you?
这让我觉得你不快乐
Which makes me think you're unhappy.
我的工作很重要
My work is important.
我从来都没真正弄明白你的工作到底是什么
I've never quite understood what it is.
这颜色适合我吗
Is this my colour?
当然
Of course it is.
我觉得你应该需要它
I thought you might need it.
我知道你怕冷
I know how you feel the cold.
他们会把它偷走的
They'll steal it.
不 他们不会
No, they won't.
你的那位军官朋友怎么样了
How's your officer?
你说他不是波兰人
He's not Polish, you said.
法国人
French.
你那位法国人是位绅士吗
Your Frenchman's a gentleman?
他再也不是我的男人了
He's not my gentleman anymore.
抱歉 请问你是谁
I'm sorry ,who are you?
我是Armand 钢琴演奏家
I'm Armand. The piano player.
顺便说一句 你的钢琴该调一调音了
And yours needs tuning, by the way.
啊 你是Gabrielle的朋友
Oh, you're Gabrielle's friend.
不止如此 上校
A little more than that, Colonel.
你在这儿干嘛 为什么我不知道你要来
What are you doing here? Why didn't I know you were coming?
因为你一直找借口对我们避而不见
Because you'd have found some excuse not to see us.
你最近过得好吗
How are you?
你看起来很糟糕
You look terrible.
James Joyce说
James Joyce said that
爱尔兰是唯一一个从未迫害过犹太人的国家
Ireland is the only country that has never persecuted the Jews.
你知道为什么吗
Do you know why?
不知道 为什么
No, why?
因为他们不让犹太人入境
Because they never let them in!
越来越多的犹太人跑到巴黎来了
More and more Jewish people are coming to Paris.
很多人到我的店里来
Many of them come to my stall,
试着卖些画和珠宝
trying to sell paintings, jewellery.
当他们变卖家当的时候
And when they've sold them,
他们打算又何去何从呢
where do they plan to go? Hmm?
巴勒斯坦?  或是美国?
Palestine? America?
我没有古董可卖
I don't have an art collection to sell.
我想我可以在远洋轮船上弹钢琴
I guess I could always play piano on an ocean liner
如果战争爆发 就在哈瓦那弃船登陆
if the war breaks out, jump ship in Havana.
你可以到赌场里弹琴
You could play in a casino
而我则做个卖香烟的女郎
and I'll be the cigarette girl.
老天啊 你们两个 严肃点儿
For God's sake, you two, be serious.
这种我们所拥有的 所热爱的生活
This life we have, this life we love,
你们都认为是理所当然
you take for granted.
但这一切都会消散  就是那样
It could all vanish. Just like that.
那你有什么好建议呢
So what do you suggest?
我们要每天都生活在对未来的恐惧中么
We live every day afraid of tomorrow?
我们就是这么熬过来的
That's how we were living.
现在好一点了 多亏了你哥哥
A little less now, thanks to your brother.
至少我们知道明天会是怎样
At least be aware of what tomorrow might be.
人们表现的就好像最坏的境况永远不会发生
People act as though the worst will never happen.
这就是你的做法吧
That's just how you act yourself.
你怎么能这么说
How can you say that?
你什么都不做
You don't do anything about anything.
除了喝遍父亲酒窖里的藏酒
Apart from drink your way through Father's cellar.
你觉得你父亲会介意我们 呃 再喝一瓶
Do you think your father would mind if we, er, drank another one?
请便
Help yourself.
恕我离席告退了
If you'll excuse me.
晚安
Good night.
- 晚安   - 晚安
- Good night.  - Good night.
Emile看见了他们两个
Emile saw the pair of them.
正在开车向南边草地的树林而去
Driving up to the woods above the south meadow.
就是你给我说过的那两个
The two you described to me.
你待在这儿
You stay here.
当然了 长官
Of course, sir.
上校要上哪儿去
Where's the Colonel going?
今天晚饭时我们就知道了
We'll find out at dinner tonight.
我们需要铁锹
We need shovels.
都怪我
I blame myself.
苏联方面知道你们在华沙联系的人是我
The Soviets knew it was me you approached in Warsaw.
他们迟早会把这些联系起来的
They were bound to make the connection sooner or later.
所以那些来的人...?
So these men who came...?
我都处理好了
I've dealt with that situation.
Fernand开他们的车去里昂了
Fernand is driving their car to Lyon.
然后在某处弃车
He'll dump it somewhere.
那我们呢
And us?
我昨晚已经和巴黎方面说过了 今早又谈了一次
I spoke to Paris last night and again this morning.
你们将要前往布列塔尼
You're going to Brittany,
显然 那是一个可爱的小山村 还靠着海
a pretty village, apparently, on the sea.
我会把你们送到巴黎
I'll drive you as far as Paris.
你也会一起离开么
You're leaving too?
是的  我妹妹说得对
Yes. My sister's right.
我在这儿不问世事的时间够久了
I've been buried here for too long.
我给你买了这个
I brought you these.
噢
Oh.
我还以为会是松露巧克力呢
I was rather hoping for truffles.
难道它们不是在你那一带出产的么
Don't they come from your neck of the woods?
看起来你并不需要它们  你怎么了
You don't look like you need them. What was it?
胆结石  怎么就得上胆结石了
Gallstones. How on earth does one get gallstones?
跟鹅肝和熟食打交道打了50年
50 years of foie gras and charcuterie?
胡说
Rubbish.
你来这儿干什么
So why are you here?
我得去工作 将军
I need to go to work, General.
我得回归这场博弈
I need to get back in the game.
最近 我们与波兰人在他们遭遇入侵的事件上
Recently, we reached an agreement with the Poles
达成了共识
in the event of their being invaded.
我们在讨论的是一项非常危险的任务
We're talking about a very dangerous mission.
这关乎他们的国家主权与未来的长期生存
It's essential to their sovereignty and long-term survival.
这件事目前只有若干最高级别的人知情
It's only known to a few at the highest possible level.
我本来派了一个人两天后出发
I had a man leaving in two days.
但你更了解波兰人  你能代替他
But you know the Poles better. You can replace him.
多谢了
Thank you.
我希望能够了解近几个月来
I'd like to see whatever
你从Elter那里得到的情况 不论那是什么
you've received from Elter in the last few months.
最近都是些无聊事
Rather dull reading recently,
不过我会和Lessard安排一下的
but I'll arrange it with Lessard.
当你从华沙回来后 我就该出院了
And when you get back from Warsaw, I'll be out of this place
我们就可以享用一顿异常美好的午餐
and we can enjoy a really good lunch.
你的医生同意么
Will your doctors allow it?
我才不邀请他们
I won't invite them.
那么 你认为你可以从这儿找出
So, you think you can find
一些被我们遗漏的东西 是么
things in here that we missed, is that it?
并非如此  我只是想重新
Not at all. I just want to
了解形式  已经有一段时间了
get back in the picture. It's been a while.
然而你却你就要去执行我等凡人
And yet you're off on a high-priority mission
眼中的最高优先级任务了
which is classified to us mere mortals.
我了解波兰  我有线人和关系网
I know Poland. I have contacts and connections.
并且Beauvilliers会支持你的
And Beauvilliers behind you.
如果战争爆发了任务便不会持续多长时间
That won't last long if war breaks out.
你也说了是 如果
You still say "If".
我在这儿安排了一场会议
I've set the meeting in here.
你以前的公寓还是空的 所以你还可以住在那儿
Your old apartment's empty so you can stay there.
不过 恐怕没有管家了
No housekeeper, I'm afraid.
你能和我们待多久
How long will you be with us?
也许是两天
Two days, perhaps.
噢 真可惜  没了你可就什么都不同了
Oh, what a shame. It's not the same without you.
你后来和Anna联系了吗
Have you been in touch with Anna?
目前她在纽约
She's in New York at the moment.
纽约  天呐
New York! Goodness.
国联在世界博览会上有一个展馆
The League has a pavilion at the World's Fair.
噢 Mercier  阴魂不散 嗯?
Ah, Mercier! Couldn't stay away, huh?
呃 你希望我在这场会议里出席么
Erm, do you want me to sit in on this meeting?
真谢谢你 那无关紧要
Thank you, that won't be necessary.
啊 我知道  那么你没什么需要的了
Ah, I see. So there's nothing that you need?
来杯咖啡还是很不错的
Coffee would be nice.
显然 德军会从西边进攻
Obviously the Germans will attack from the west,
所以我们的路线得是东南方 进入罗马尼亚
so our route has to be south-east, into Romania.
我们的外交部已经向布加勒斯特提议了
Our Foreign Ministry has already made overtures with Bucharest.
Bucharest 罗马尼亚首都
将会有一艘货轮出现在黑海的康斯坦察
There'll be a freighter at Constanza on the Black Sea.
升着中立的旗子
It will fly a neutral flag
但是配有法国船员和一艘武装的护卫舰
but have a French crew and an armed escort.
货物经由马赛
It will take the consignment to Marseilles.
最终抵达苏黎世
Ultimate destination - Zurich.
我希望你是那个监守全程的人
I want you to be the person who sees it through.
我会的
I'll insist on it.
当然 我希望永远不要走到这一步
Of course, I hope it never comes to this.
我们都知道这不可避免
We both know it will.
我上次在这儿的时候
When I was last here,
我得到了一个促使我在
I got a tip that led to
柏林的IN6里插入一个线人的暗示
me setting up an informant in IN6 in Berlin.
有什么想和我说的么
Anything to share with me?
你不会想知道的
You wouldn't want it.
在最后的两天我一直都在整理所有最新的材料
I've been over all the recent material in the last two days.
我认为材料有问题
I think it's tainted.
Lapp博士在华沙么
Is Doctor Lapp in Warsaw?
他在  怎么了
He is. Why?
Lapp就是那个给了我暗示的人
It was Lapp who gave me the tip.
恐怕自我们上次见面后
The world has not improved
这世道仍旧一点儿都没改变
since we saw each other last, I fear.
我在柏林见着你的时候
When I saw you in Berlin,
我很感谢你那慎重的态度
I was grateful for your discretion.
如果战争爆发了
If war does break out,
你将会理解我必须效忠自己的祖国
you will understand that I must serve my country,
- 无论她的领导人是谁   - 当然
- whoever its leaders.  - Of course.
我得感谢你帮我联系上了Halbach
I wanted to thank you for the Halbach connection.
据我所知 他是安全的
As far as I know, he's safe.
是的 我听说了
Yes, I had heard that.
然后你又去联系他了么
And did it lead you to his contact?
还是说是我多嘴了
Or am I asking too much?
我去了  他很有用
It did. He's been very useful.
除了我觉着他已经暴露了
Except I think he's been exposed.
投敌了
Turned.
拿纳粹想让我们相信的东西来迷惑我们
Feeding us what the Nazis want us to believe.
真的
Really?
你为何如此判断
What makes you think so?
他情报的质量
The quality of his intelligence.
你在柏林有着强大的关系网 博士
You have powerful connections in Berlin, Doctor.
是否有可能证实我的怀疑?
Would it be possible to confirm my suspicions?
- 这些都被第二局曝光了么   - 没有
- Are they shared by the Deuxieme Bureau?  - No.
法国第二局:法国情报机关
目前为止我还没有走漏任何风声
So far I've kept this to myself.
我建议你如此
I suggest you do,
直到我完成一些调查
until I have made some enquiries.
我会谨慎的 不过
I will be discreet, but...
我们都处在危险的边缘 你和我
we are on dangerous ground, you and I.
在我向Lapp博士吐露秘密后的不到几小时
A few hours after I confided in Doctor Lapp,
巴黎
就有人进来想要杀我
someone came to kill me.
所以我只能假设他是想我保持沉默
So I can only assume he was trying to silence me.
如果我能成功说服我上司
If I convinced my superiors of my suspicions,
那么Elter那条线对于纳粹来说将是无用的
then the Elter pipeline would be useless to the Nazis.
你认为Lapp让你出面
You think Lapp set you up in the first place
- 去发现Elter的身份   - 我确信
- to discover Elter's identity?  - Convinced of it.
你让Pakulski逮捕他了么
Did you get Pakulski to arrest him?
没有证据  没人能逮捕他
There's no evidence. Nothing they can hold him on.
并且 如果你知道了谁是你的敌人
Besides, if you know who your enemy is,
有时最好让他处于活跃状态
it's sometimes best to keep him in play.
这真是个饱受摧残 扭曲了的间谍世界
What a tortured, twisted business this espionage is.
你想除了胆结石之外再患上痛风吗
Do you want to add gout to gallstones?
我在医院里时可都梦想着这些呢
I dreamed of this when I was in hospital.
你认为Angela女士有多重要?
How seriously do you regard Lady Angela?
她可能看起来比较轻浮 但她和丘吉尔身边的人
She may seem frivolous but she has very good connections
保持着密切的联系
with people who have Churchill's ear.
你能否把事情提到议案里
Can you put things in motion?
噢 比你想象的要快多了
Oh, sooner than you think.
三国会议
注释:苏 英 法三国军备制定会议
1939年7月
- 我确信就是他   - 但是很明显
- I'm sure he is.  - But clearly,
- 在这一点上务必要谨慎考虑   - 是的
- discretion is called for at this point.  - Yes.
Mercier上校
Colonel Mercier,
我来向你介绍Duff Cooper
I'd like to introduce Duff Cooper.
你在这儿有着良好的声誉 上校
You have sympathetic ears here, Colonel.
这是我对于比利时的分析
This is my analysis of the Belgian scenario.
虽然我应该加上一些
Though I should add that some
我上司所不信任的东西
of my superiors don't give it much credence.
我们会再见的 上校 大概就在今晚稍晚的时候
We'll meet again, Colonel, possibly later tonight.
我把这个留给你 Angela
I leave that to you, Angela.
Duff是丘吉尔的私人秘书
Duff is Churchill's Private Secretary,
所以你的报告是不会在托盘上摞着吃灰的
so your report won't gather dust in an in-tray.
如果他们的反应良好
If they respond well,
你可能就想横渡英吉利海峡继续调查了
you might want to follow this up with a trip across the Channel.
这任务不显得太繁重了么
Not too onerous a mission?
乘午夜的卧铺和夫人前去伦敦
A midnight sleeper to London with Her Ladyship.
我觉着如果我们飞去的话会更安全
I think it might be safer if we flew.
顺便问一下 谁是那个守口如瓶的人
By the way, who was that man who didn't say anything?
他在我们的布局里
He's in our game.
我记得他名字是Philby
I think his name's Philby.
看到什么了
What is it?
Max Mostov
Max Mostov!
上帝啊  潇洒的中校
God in heaven! The dashing Colonel.
英俊如昔啊
Handsome as ever, I see.
我还以为你死了  或者进了集中营
I assumed you were dead. Or in a gulag.
我很幸运  他们弄坏了我的指关节
I was fortunate. They gave me a rap on the knuckles,
然后把我丢进了监狱里关了几个月
then threw me in jail for a few months.
然后他们送你去巴黎休养生息?
And then they send you to Paris to recuperate?
你这个骗子
You're a liar.
你是他们中的一员  你一直都是
You're one of theirs. You always were.
你骗过了所有人 我承认
You had us all fooled, I give you that.
你知道 当你一直都和
You know, when you are always
根本不清楚你的真面目 或是从不知道
with people who don't know who you really are,
你的秘密的那些人在一起时
who do not know that secret part of you,
那会让你觉得 在某种程度上高人一等
it makes you feel, in a way, above them.
你认为那是吸引力么
Do you think that's the appeal?
那些对我来说毫无吸引力
Nothing about that appeals to me.
过去的就过去了
Water under the bridge.
这是我们两个之间的疯狂交易 嘿
This is a crazy business of ours, hey?
看看我们
Look at us.
现在我们可是并肩作战的战友
Now we are comrades in arms,
苏联和法国联合起来共同反对可怕的希特勒
Soviets and French united against the dreaded Hitler.
我们应该为这个喝一杯
We should drink to this.
我可不想与你共饮 Max
I don't want to drink with you, Max.
请便
Suit yourself.
我听说你和可爱的Anna处得可并不怎么好啊
I hear it did not go so well with you and the lovely Anna.
她在你身上浪费了太多毫无意义的眼泪
She wasted a lot of pointless tears on you.
我告诉你
And I tell you something.
我会让她回心转意
I would have her back.
易如反掌
Just like that!
我想用我这双手亲手掐死他
I wanted to strangle him with my bare hands.
之后我冷静下来并且意识到 我得告诉Anna
Then I calmed down and realised, I have to tell Anna.
这将会使一切都变得不同
It's going to make all the difference.
那你去了么
And have you?
还没有  她还在从纽约回来的途中
Not yet. She's on her way back from New York.
这是你生命中的真爱么
Is this the love of your life?
我生命中的第二度挚爱
The second love of my life.
Armand是我的第三个
Armand's my third.
前两个真的算不上
The first two don't really count.
谢了
Thank you.
如果战争开始了 你们的爱情将会受到严峻的考验
Your love will be put to the test if there's a war.
因为Armand是个犹太人?
Because Armand's a Jew?
也许他应该坐船到哈瓦那
Maybe he should take that boat to Havana.
他不会离开巴黎的  并且也不会离开我
He won't leave Paris. And he won't leave me.
抱歉打断你们
Forgive the intrusion.
我能加入你们一会吗
May I join you for a moment?
当然可以 请坐
Of course, please.
你想私下谈话吗
Do you want to talk in private?
不 亲爱的
No, my dear.
到早上整个世界就都会知道的
The whole world will know when it wakes up in the morning.
第二局已经
The Deuxieme Bureau has
拦截了德国大使馆的情报
picked up an intercept to the German Embassy.
希特勒与斯大林签署了互不侵犯条约
Hitler has signed a non-aggression pact with Stalin.
什么
What?
两个相互抗衡了多年的人
Two men who vilified each other for years.
他们会让Machiavell感到骄傲的
They'd make Machiavelli proud.
马基亚维利:意大利哲学家 《君主论》作者
希特勒曾受其作品思想启发
就在几天前 俄国人们还带着他们乏味的微笑和
Only days ago, the Russians were at that conference
糟糕的西装出席了那次会议
with their bland smiles and bad suits.
他们与我们签署了合约
They signed an agreement with us!
这意味着什么
And what does this mean?
这是一个卑鄙的 嘲讽的战术 这样俄国
It's a vile and cynical tactic so that Russia
可以和德国一起瓜分波兰
and Germany can carve up Poland between them.
战争已无可避免 只是时间问题
War is inevitable, a matter of days.
你们得尽快离开
You must leave as soon as possible.
华沙
噢 我亲爱的姑娘
Oh, my dear girl,
波兰现在时局很糟糕 非常糟
what a terrible time for Poland, terrible.
您怎么来了
What are you doing here?
Mercier上校让我来接你
Colonel Mercier asked me to meet you.
他大概一天之内会到华沙
He should be in Warsaw in
他不顾一切地要见你
a day or so and he's desperate to see you.
我不想看到他
I don't wish to see him.
在你听了他让我告诉你的事情后
I think you might, my dear,
你也许就不会这么想了
when you hear what he's asked me to tell you.
是关于Max的
It's about Max.
Malka 我们会永远活在恐惧之中
Malka, we will always be afraid.
无论是作为叛逃者还是犹太人
Either as defectors or Jews.
我们身边的都是陌生人
We live among strangers.
不知道谁会第一个将矛头指向我们
Who knows who will be the first to point the finger?
这样我们就能在一起了 永远在一起
This way we will be together, always.
很高兴见到你 上校
Good to see you, Colonel.
我也是 Marek 这边情况怎么样
You too, Marek. What's the mood here?
所有40岁以下的人必须响应召集令
Everyone under 40 has to collect call-up papers.
加上所有的预备役军人和退伍军人
Plus all reservists and ex-soldiers.
你不是吗
Not you?
上校想让我跟着你做这个任务
The Colonel wants me on this assignment you're on.
他不会告诉我是什么
He won't tell me what it is.
你要我做什么
What do you want from me?
首先 从现在起
First, your silence about
对你的一切所见所闻保持沉默
everything you see and hear from now on.
我要你撤掉车厢内所有的座位
I need all the seats ripped out of those coaches
车底板腾出位置来放板条箱
and the floorboards taken up to make room for some crates.
明早之前我要车上恢复原状
Everything needs to be back in place by tomorrow morning.
是军火吗
Is it ammunition?
我是说 我要知道这个东西是不是随时会爆炸
I mean, I need to know if this thing could blow up at any minute.
我不能告诉你是什么
I can't tell you what it is.
我还要驾驶?
And I'm supposed to drive it?
你不就是干这个的嘛
That's what you do, isn't it?
干了40年了 没错
For 40 years, yes.
这还是原定的计划吗
Was this the original plan?
自从那些混蛋出其不意地占领我们之后 一切都变了
Everything's changed since those bastards took us by surprise.
我们只得随机应对
We're improvising.
我们什么时候走
So when will we leave?
一大早走
Not before morning.
我要去大使馆登记
I'll check in with the Embassy.
噢 昨晚 厚脸皮出现在Cleo咖啡馆
Oh! Last night. Bold as brass in the Cafe Cleo.
Lapp博士 以他的咖啡和法国白兰地
Dr Lapp, with his coffee and his cognac, expressing his regret
对发生在我们两个伟大的国家间的事情
that these things have
表达了他的惋惜
come to pass between our two great nations.
他还在这?
He's still here?
是的
Yes.
有什么消息
What have you heard?
德国坦克向波兰进发
German tanks are heading for Poland.
52个师 是150万人
52 divisions, that's a million and a half men.
而斯大林在我们的东部边界有40个师
And Stalin has 40 divisions on our eastern border.
他们会先炸飞机场 然后是电话局
They'll bomb the airfields first. Then telephone exchanges.
你们什么时候离开
When will you get out?
我们在等巴黎的消息 你一直都是对的
We're waiting for Paris to tell us. You were right all along.
我要把这个给大使
I'll take this to the Ambassador.
Anna呢
Anna?
我见过她了 我把Max的事告诉她了
I saw her. I told her about Max.
然后?
And?
震惊 流泪 悔恨
Shock. Tears. Regret.
我要见她 她在哪
I have to see her. Where is she?
她去乡下陪她母亲了
She went to the country to be with her mother.
我知道地址
I have an address.
为什么把我带到到这么可怕的地方
Why have I been brought to this dreadful place?
你被指控为间谍 Lapp博士
You're accused of espionage, Dr Lapp.
被谁指控的?
Accused by whom?
Mercier上校
Colonel Mercier.
太可恶了
That's outrageous.
他没有证据
He has no evidence.
我们不需要证据
We don't need evidence.
我们并不是在监禁你
We are not arresting you.
我们是根据紧急权力法拘留你
We are detaining you under the Emergency Powers Act.
根本没有这种东西!
There's no such thing!
这是我们将要被敌对外国势力
It's what we enact when we're
入侵时颁布的法律
about to be invaded by a hostile foreign power.
我要求跟我大使馆的人说话
I demand to speak to someone from my Embassy.
您的要求我们会充分考虑的
Your demand is duly noted.
现在 请给我您的腰带和鞋
Now, give me your belt and shoes.
那边还有多少
How many more of those are there?
另外两货车的量
Another two truckloads.
总重多少
What's the total weight?
大约40,000千克
About 40,000 kilograms.
这比塞满了人的火车还要重
That's more than the average train packed with passengers.
我们不用很快的速度
We don't need to be fast,
只要看起来像普通列车就行
we just need to look like an ordinary train.
1939年 9月1日
波兰 莫卡拉村
睡着了吗
Did you sleep?
几乎没有
Hardly.
战争开始了
It's started.
德国突击队已经越过边界
German commando units have crossed the border,
他们有6个装甲师和8个机械化装备师的支援
backed up by six armoured and eight motorized divisions.
上帝保佑 我们开战了
God preserve us, we're at war.
我们可以来点你的苏格兰威士忌
We could have some of your decent Scotch
如果还有的话
if there's any left.
我会带着的
I'll bring it with me.
走吧 车在外面
Let's go. Car's outside.
安娜母亲的房子
Anna's mother's estate is
离我们路线上的一个站只有30分钟的距离
just 30 minutes from a station on our route.
那个地方叫博雷克
A place called Borek.
我要去接她 在这里跟你碰面
I'm going to get her and meet you there.
你不能去 你有命令在身
You are not. You have orders.
Antoni 我只需要几个小时
I'm asking for a few hours, Antoni.
拒绝请求 你知道我们要在这做什么
Request denied. You know what we have to do here.
我的正式任务是从罗马尼亚边界开始的
My official mission begins at the Romanian border.
不 你正式任务从这里开始 就现在 跟我一起
No, your official mission begins here, now, with me.
如果你危害任务 那么我们军事法庭上见
And if you jeopardise it, I'll see you are court-martialled.
我会回到火车上的
I will make it back to the train.
要是出了差错
If something goes wrong,
你会被滞留在波兰中部
you'll be stranded in the middle of Poland
俄国人和德国人会分别从两个方向攻进来
with Russians coming one way and Germans the other.
死在爱人的怀里 这对你算是慰藉吗
So you die in your lover's arms, that will console you?
我一定要去
I have to do this.
Jean-Francois 你是我的朋友
Jean-Francois, you are my friend.
我们是20年的朋友了
We've been friends for 20 years.
但是 如果你没有出现在那个站
But if you're not at that station,
我一分钟都不会等
I won't wait even a minute.
我明白
I understand.
这些孩子从哪来的
Where did these children come from?
从城里来的 母亲 对他们而言这里更安全
From the city, Mother. It's safer for them here.
我过去很喜欢仆人的小孩玩闹的声音
I used to love the sound of the servants' children
当这房子还是我们的时候
when the house was ours.
有时他们会忘记给我们做午餐
Sometimes they forget about our lunch.
大部分护士都离开了
Most of the nurses have left.
现在是战争时期 妈妈 战争已经开始了
We're at war, Mother. It's started.
我的两个兄弟在上一次战争中死去
My two brothers died in the last one.
Patryk那时只有18岁
Patryk was only 18.
但他们说再也不会有下一次战争了
But they said there would never be another one.
昨天的汤是凉的
The soup was cold yesterday.
你来这干嘛
What are you doing here?
我来接你 Anna
I've come for you, Anna.
你在内疚与泪水中荒废了一年
You wasted a year on guilt and tears.
我们生命中本该共度的一年
A year of our lives we should have spent with each other.
我当初多么愚蠢 我全都相信了
What a stupid woman I was. I believed it all.
我本以为Max是需要拯救的灵魂
I thought Max was a soul that needed saving.
那都是欺骗你的 我一直很想念你
It was all a deception. I've missed you.
你最好还是把我引见给你的母亲吧
You'd better introduce me to your mother.
妈妈
Mother,
这是Jean-Francois Mercier上校
this is Colonel Jean-Francois Mercier.
荣幸之至 女士
An honour, Ma'am.
的确是个绅士
A gentleman indeed.
你能来拜访我们真是太好了
How kind of you to come and visit us.
没有别人这样做过
No-one else ever does.
我要你们跟我一起走
I want you both to come with me.
- 去哪?   - 离开波兰
- Where to?   - Out of Poland.
我们得赶上20千米外的一趟火车
We have to pick up a train 20 kilometres from here.
所以越快越好 带的东西越少越好
So be as quick as you can, take as little as you need.
你来自巴黎?  我喜爱我们住在巴黎的日子
Are you from Paris?  I loved it when we lived in Paris.
我们住在那家有名的面包店旁
We were near that famous bakery.
妈妈 您听到上校说的了 我们得离开了
Mother, you heard the Colonel. We have to leave.
我没有去巴黎穿的衣服
I don't have the clothes for Paris.
又是新的潮流了 可你必须要走 Anna
It will be all new fashions. You must go, Anna.
不行 我不会把你留在这的
No! I won't leave you here.
但你应该这么做
But you should.
你恋爱了
You're in love.
你还有大好青春
You have a life ahead of you.
而我已风烛残年
Mine's behind me.
我看见火车的烟了 看那边
I can see smoke. Look!
我们要减速吗
Do we slow down?
如果他不在就不用了
Not if he's not there.
他没有停
He's not stopping!
那辆车 是他的车 上校
The car. It's the car, Colonel.
上校?
Colonel?
刹车!
Hit the brakes!
你时间掐得很紧
You cut it fine.
谢天谢地 我有一辆法国车
Thank God I had a French car.
很高兴见到你 Anna
Good to see you, Anna.
好了 走吧
OK, let's go.
我们正在前往边界
We're heading for the border.
你 Pakulski 还有武装护卫
You, Pakulski, armed guards.
怎么回事
What's going on?
我们有一批隐蔽的货物
We have a hidden cargo.
在我们脚下?
Under our feet?
是什么?
What is it?
我们正在疏散波兰全部的国家金银储备
We're evacuating the entire Polish national bullion reserve.
抢在纳粹染指之前
Before the Nazis can get their hands on it.
黄金?
Gold?
40箱 每箱10锭
40 cases. 10 ingots in every case.
-送到罗马尼亚?   -还有更远的地方
-To Romania? -And beyond.
我是Vladimir Herschensohn
Vladimir Herschensohn.
波兰国家交响乐团的首席小提琴手
Principal violinist of the Polish National Symphony Orchestra.
我是Roman Kosinksi
Roman Kosinksi.
噢 是学生?
Oh, a student?
原来是 现在我都不知道自己是什么了
I was. Now I've no idea what I am.
而且我可能再也见不到我的家人了
And I may never see my family again.
你要相信你会见到他们的
You must believe that you will.
相信他们会活下来 你自己也会活下来
That they will survive and so will you.
脊髓灰质炎你都幸免于难了
You survived polio.
我们是朝罗马尼亚的方向去吗
Is it true we are headed for Romania?
他们是这么说的
So they say.
我有表亲住那
Ah, I have cousins there.
他们有个不错的管弦乐队
They have a fine orchestra.
如果他们不接纳我 我就只能在街头卖艺了
If they won't have me, it will mean a cap on the pavement.
你会回去打仗吗 上校
Will you go back to fight this war, Colonel?
我们俩都会
We both will.
怎么了?
你没听见早些时候的爆炸声吗?
我们的军队已经很近了
守卫都走了
我们能出去了
停下来 别跑
Stop! Stop!
别开枪
我们是德国人
德国人!
谢谢你们告诉我们 我们是波兰人
Good of you to let us know. We're Polish.
怎么了
What's happening?
那有个女孩
There's a girl.
怎么了
What's happened?
我不确定 你待在这
I'm not sure, stay here.
你们两个跟我来
You two with me.
来 拿着这个
Here, take this.
我不知道这个怎么用
I don't know how to use this.
我来教你 我并不总是在拉小提琴的
I'll show you. I didn't always play the violin.
上去
Get in.
有问题吗
Is something wrong?
求你了 阁下
Please, Excellency.
带我一起走
Take me with you.
待在这 不要忘了金条
Stay here, don't leave the bullion.
我去看看发生什么了
I'm going to see what's happening.
你不用付我钱的
You don't have to pay me.
你住在哪 你的家人呢
Where do you live? Where is your family?
都走了
Gone.
我不会说你们的话
I don't speak your language.
你是谁
Who are you?
我在铁路公司工作
I work for the railroad.
你看起来不像铁路工人啊
You don't look like railroad worker.
火车上有什么值钱的东西吗
Anything valuable on this train?
只有人 去往边界
Just people, heading for the border.
逃跑哈?
Running, huh?
为什么不呢
Why not?
波兰人完蛋了
The Poles are finished.
你想要什么
What do you want from us?
钱 珠宝 女人
Money. Jewellery. Women.
别担心 丑的我们不要
Don't worry, we won't take ugly ones.
把那块表给我
Give me that watch.
你在铁路公司上班怎么可能有这个
You don't get this working for railroad.
你看那下面干什么
What do you see down there?
你还好吗
Are you all right?
还好 还有两个在车厢里
Fine. There's two more back in the carriage,
他们走不了了
they're not going anywhere.
对不起 他们逼我的
I'm sorry. They make me.
为什么我们不在野外的小屋定居下来
Why don't we settle in a cabin in the wild -
一口井 养几只山羊
a well, a few goats
远离这场战争
and hundreds of miles from the war?
我还要几只狗 几本书
I'd need dogs. And some books.
还有一个好酒窖
And a good cellar.
我还会学会缝纫
And I'd learn to sew.
我们到哪了
Where are we anyway?
明天我们会抵达边界
We'll reach the border tomorrow.
然后?
And then?
我不会再让你离开我的视线
I'll never let you out of my sight.
可能四到五周内到法国 我们就结婚
Could be in France in four or five weeks, we'll get married.
如果你要我成为一个体面的女人
If you want to make a respectable woman of me,
恐怕太晚了
I'm afraid you're too late.
我还可以试试
I can still try.
跟预想的一样
Looks like we're expected.
如果跟罗马尼亚人的交涉得不错的话
If it goes well with the Romanians,
之后的就全由你做主了
the rest is up to you.
退一步说 未来充满了不确定
The future is uncertain, to say the least.
无论发生什么 你们俩要共同面对
Whatever it may be, you two face it together.
现在该怎么办
What now?
竭尽所能活下来
We do our best to stay alive.
1939年12月
150万德国军队涌入波兰
波兰的黄金储备经过罗马尼亚
通过土耳其和黎巴嫩
于10月到达巴黎
战争结束时
800,00华沙人死去
90%的老城成为废墟